Chris Anderson: William, hi. Good to see you.
كريس أنديسون: ويليام، مرحبا. سررت بلقائك
William Kamkwamba: Thanks.
ويليلم كامكوامبا: شكرا
CA: So, we've got a picture, I think? Where is this?
ك.أ.: إذا لدينا صورة، أعتقد؟ أين هذه؟
WK: This is my home. This is where I live.
و.ك.: هذا منزلي. حيث أقطن
CA: Where? What country?
ك.أ.: أين؟ أي دولة؟
WK: In Malawi, Kasungu. In Kasungu. Yeah, Mala.
و.ك.: في مالاوي، كاسونجو. نعم. مالا
CA: OK. Now, you're 19 now?
ك.أ.: حسنا. الآن، أنت التاسعة عشر اليس كذلك؟
WK: Yeah. I'm 19 years now.
و.ك.: نعم. أنا في التاسعة عشر الآن
CA: Five years ago you had an idea. What was that?
ك.أ.: منذ خمس أعوام خطرت لك فكرة. ما هي؟
WK: I wanted to make a windmill.
و.ك.: أردت صنع طاحونة هوائية
CA: A windmill?
ك.أ.: طاحونة هوائية؟
WK: Yeah.
و.ك.: نعم
CA: What, to power -- for lighting and stuff?
ك.أ.: إذا -- ماذا -- للطاقة -- للإضائة وما شابه؟
CA: So what did you do? How did you realize that?
ك.أ.: ماذا فعلت؟ كيف حققت ذلك؟
WK: After I dropped out of school, I went to library,
و.ك.: بعد خروجي من المدرسة، ذهبت إلى المكتبة
and I read a book that would -- "Using Energy,"
وقرأت كتابا عن "إستخدام الطاقة"ـ
and I get information about doing the mill.
وحصلت على المعلومات اللازمة لصنعها
And I tried, and I made it.
وحاولت وصنعتها
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CA: So you copied -- you exactly copied the design in the book.
ك.أ.: إذا نسخت -- قمت بنسخ التصميم كما هو في الكتاب
WK: Ah, no. I just --
و.ك.: آه، لا. أنا فقط
CA: What happened?
ك.أ.: ماذا حدث؟
WK: In fact, a design of the windmill that was in the book,
و.ك.: في الواقع، كان تصميم الطاحونة الهوائية في الكتاب
it has got four -- ah -- three blades,
بأربع -- آه -- بل ثلاث ريش
and mine has got four blades.
وطاحونتي لها أربع ريش
CA: The book had three, yours had four.
ك.أ.: الكتاب له ثلاثة وأنت لديك أربع
WK: Yeah.
و.ك.: نعم
CA: And you made it out of what?
ك.أ.: ومما صنعتها؟
WK: I made four blades, just because I want to increase power.
و.ك.: صنعت أربع ريش، فقط لأنني أردت أن أزيد في الطاقة
CA: OK.
ك.أ.: حسنا
WK: Yeah.
و.ك.: نعم
CA: You tested three, and found that four worked better?
ك.أ.: جربت ثلاثة، ووجدت أن أربع تعمل أفضل؟
WK: Yeah. I test.
و.ك.: نعم. جربت
CA: And what did you make the windmill out of?
ك.أ.: ومما صنعت الطاحونة؟
What materials did you use?
ماذا -- المواد التي إستخدمتها؟
WK: I use a bicycle frame, and a pulley, and plastic pipe, what then pulls --
استعملت إطار دراجة، وبكرة ، وأنابيب بلاستيكية، ثم تسحب
CA: Do we have a picture of that? Can we have the next slide?
ك.أ.: هل لدينا صورة لذلك؟ هلا أظهرتم الشريحة التالية؟
WK: Yeah. The windmill.
و.ك.: نعم. الطاحونة الهوائية
CA: And so, and that windmill, what -- it worked?
ك.أ.: إذا، هذه الطاحونة، ماذا -- هل عملت؟
WK: When the wind blows, it rotates and generates.
و.ك.: حين تهب الرياح، تدور وتولد
CA: How much electricity?
ك.أ.: كم من الطاقة؟
WK: 12 watts.
و.ك.: 12 واط
CA: And so, that lit a light for the house? How many lights?
ك.أ.: إذا، هذا أنار المنزل كله؟ كم لمبة؟
WK: Four bulbs and two radios.
و.ك.: أربع لمبات وراديو ين
CA: Wow.
ك.أ.: واو
WK: Yeah.
و.ك.: نعم
(Applause) CA: Next slide --
ك.أ.: إذا -- (تصفيق) -- الشريحة التالية
so who's that?
من هذا؟
WK: This is my parents, holding the radio.
و.ك.: هؤلاء والديّ، أحضرا الراديو
CA: So what did they make of -- that you were 14, 15 at the time --
ك.أ.: فكيف كانت ردة فعلهم؟ كنت في الرابعة عشر أو الخامسة عشر حينها
what did they make of this? They were impressed?
ماذا كانت ردة فعلهم؟ هل أعجبوا؟
WK: Yeah.
و.ك.: نعم
CA: And so what's your -- what are you going to do with this?
ك.أ.: إذا ما هي -- ماذا ستفعل بهذا؟
WK: Um --
و.ك.: آم
CA: What do you -- I mean -- do you want to build another one?
ك.أ.: ماذا تنوي -- أعني -- هل تود بناء أخرى؟
WK: Yeah, I want to build another one --
و.ك.: نعم، أود بناء أخرى
to pump water and irrigation for crops.
لضخ المياه وري -- ري المحاصيل
CA: So this one would have to be bigger?
ك.أ.: إذا هذه ستكون أكبر
WK: Yeah.
و.ك.: نعم
CA: How big?
ك.أ.: ما حجمها؟
WK: I think it will produce more than 20 the watts.
و.ك.: أعتقد أنها ستنتج أكثر من 20 واط
CA: So that would produce irrigation for the entire village?
ك.أ.: هذه ستوفر الري لجميع القرية؟
WK: Yeah.
و.ك.: نعم
CA: Wow. And so you're talking to people here at TED
ك.أ.: واو. لذا تتواصل مع أناس هنا في تيد
to get people who might be able to help in some way
للحصول على أناس قد يساعدونك بطريقة ما
to realize this dream?
لتحقق هذا الحلم
WK: Yeah, if they can help me with materials, yeah.
و.ك.: نعم، إذا استطاعوا مساعدتي -- بالمواد، نعم
CA: And as you think of your life going forward,
ك.أ.: وهل تفكر بمستقبلك
you're 19 now,
أنت في التاسعة عشر الآن، هل
do you picture continuing with this dream of working in energy?
هل تتصور أن تستمر بهذا الحلم، بالعمل في الطاقة؟
WK: Yeah. I'm still thinking to work on energy.
و.ك.: نعم. لازلت أفكر بالعمل في الطاقة
CA: Wow. William, it's a real honor to have you at the TED conference.
ك.أ.: واو. ويليام، لقد كان شرفا حقيقيا حضورك في مؤتمر تيد
Thank you so much for coming.
شكرا جزيلا لقدومك
WK: Thank you.
و.ك.: شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)